A Guide to the Nancy O'Brien Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: UVA Classes
  - A. Graduate Student and Thesis
    - 1985 Thesis notes on Planning District Commissions in Virginia, 18 items (Box-folder 10:4)
      Included are notes on budget and work programs, articles by Nelson Wikstrom
    - 1985-1986 Thesis notes on Planning District Commissions in Virginia, 35 items (Box-folder 10:5)
      There is a copy of House Bill 1479 that amended Virginia Code to allow funding for the commissions. There are articles and memos about financial funding for PDC's and their role in government. There are also notes from her research on T. Marshall Hahn, and "Five Metropolitan Governments"
    - 1985 Thesis notes on Planning District Commissions in Virginia, 17 items (Box-folder 10:6)
      There are notes from speeches made by President Lyndon F. Johnson regarding government organizations and research surveys about PDCS.
    - 1985 Thesis Prospectus on Planning District Commissions in Virginia, 6 items (Box-folder 10:7)
      There are several drafts of the prospectus and some comments from Professor Stephen L. Percy.
    - 1986 Masters Thesis Planning District Commissions in Virginia, 1 item (Box-folder 11:1)
      There is a copy of Nancy O'Brien's thesis
  - B.Professor O'Brien
    - 1993-1994 O'Brien class on Federal & State Housing, 25 items (Box-folder 11:2)
      There is paperwork for UVA instructors including memos about student rolls, other correspondence about the course, reading materials, and outlines for assigned projects on housing
    - 1998 UVA class on Fifeville, 13 items (Box-folder 11:3)
      There are several copies of a neighborhood report of Fifeville and research information including census records
    - 2004 UVA class on Fifeville, 12 items (Box-folder 11:4)
      UVA Professor Nisha Botchwey taught a class on Fifeville 2003 and Beyond. There is a study of Fifeville which was researched by the students in this class. Two cd's containing information on Fifeville and the Fifeville Neighborhood Association are included.
- Series III: Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission
  - n. d. Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission, 8 items (Box-folder 12:1)
    There are outlines for a strategic plan to find common grounds among organizations in the Charlottesville community and a presentation on TJPDC extension services, Jefferson Area Bicycle, Pedestrian, and Greenway Plans. There are also a few newspaper clippings.
  - 1996 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Build Out Analysis Report, 1 item (Box-folder 12:2)
  - 1970- 1990; 1995 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Census Reports, 40 items (Box-folder 12:3)
    Included are figures for the reports and a report by the Charlottesville-Albemarle Children and Youth Commission
  - 1988- 1991 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Census Reports, 4 items (Box-folder 12:4)
    There are Albemarle County Census reports
  - 1988; 2001 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Economic and Environmental Reports, 3 items (Box-folder 12:5)
    There is a Thomas Jefferson Sustainability Council report (in which Nancy O'Brien attached notes to the reports such as "we nearly killed each other getting though this," a Regional Economic Development Plan, and an employment survey
  - 1998-1999 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Hourly Rates, 2 items (Box-folder 12:6)
    There is a list of salaries for the staff of TJPDC and a breakdown of hours worked for the fiscal year
  - 1994 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Minority Health, 2 items (Box-folder 12:7)
    There are minutes from the Minority Health Concerns Committee
  - 2001 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Poverty Studies, 25 items (Box-folder 12:8)
    Facts and figures reported by the Monticello Area Community Action Agency
  - n. d. Thomas Jefferson Housing Improvement Corporation: Retirement, 1 item (Box-folder 13:1)
    There is a photograph of Nancy O'Brien's retirement party
  - 2001 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Retirement, 4 items (Box-folder 13:2)
    There is a letter from Nancy O'Brien to Harry Harris, chair of the TJPDC regarding her remaining projects. There is also information from her release time record.
  - 1996-2001 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Tourism Reports, 2 items (Box-folder 13:3)
    There are reports on the Thomas Jefferson Venture Heritage Tourism Project. Included is a description by Nancy O'Brien about the difficulties with the project because of the different interests of the committee (economic development vs. preservation.) She also mentioned the kindness and strengths of certain individuals and a wine bottle of "Il Fiasco" that she received as a gift. (She wrote that State Senator Emily Couric made public corrections of O'Brien's statements and later called O'Brien and apologized, confessing that she was the one who had inaccurate information.)
  - 1993-1994 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission: United Way, 11 items (Box-folder 13:4)
    There is a report on the needs and priorities of the community which was based on surveys given to the community. The surveys and results are included.
  - 1991-1993 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Visions Forums, 9 items (Box-folder 13:5)
    There are transcripts of the tape record of speeches by Nancy O'Brien and other leaders of the community on their visions of the future as well as participation and discussion by the attendees.
  - 1998 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Water Report, 1 item (Box-folder 13:6)
    There is a TJPDC report on the Rivanna River Basin Project. Included is an article on the Moore's Creek Watershed.
  - 1999 Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Water Report, 1 item (Box-folder 13:7)
    There is a report on present conditions and recommendations for preservation and restoration for water resources in Fluvanna County
- Series IV: Jefferson School
  - 2001-2006 Citizens for Jefferson School, 24 items (Box-folder 13:8)
    Citizens formed a group to save Jefferson School as an educational institution and requested City Council to designate a task force to study its future usage. Included are e-mails, minutes of meetings and work sessions. There is a request for a proposal for preparing a National Historic Register Nomination and a historical architect, and plans for a Jefferson School Reunion for the classes of 1930- 1951. Newspaper clippings, photographs and information about a highway marker are also included.
  - 2002 Citizens for Jefferson School By-laws, 25 items (Box-folder 14:1)
    There are by-laws, a certificate of incorporation for the organization, Citizens for Jefferson School Steering Committee minutes, a list of members, and a proposal for a task force.
  - 2004-2005 Jefferson School as a Cultural Heritage Center, 1 notebook (Box-folder 14:2)
    Included is information on funding opportunities, e-mails, an interpretive plan, a letter from Jefferson-Madison Regional Library about space at the school, a proposal from architectural historian, Maral S. Kalbian, and design plans for a culture heritage center at Jefferson School
  - 2002-2003 Jefferson School Grants and Fund Possibilities, 15 items (Box-folder 14:3)
    There is information on grants from Bell South, Oak Hill Fund, Save America's Treasures, Mary Reynolds Babcock Foundation e-mails, and a grant application
  - 2004 Jefferson School BAMA Grants, 15 items (Box-folder 14:4)
    There is a grant application to the BAMA works fund in the Charlottesville-Albemarle Community Foundation and of the Dave Mathews Band. There is correspondence and a rough draft of the application
  - 2000-2003 Jefferson School and African American History, 12 items (Box-folder 15:1)
    There is a typed copy of the School Board minutes from 1922 about expanding the Jefferson Colored School; a history of Jefferson School, and African American history in Charlottesville including a petition to save Jefferson School, a newsletter The New Jeffersonian, an oral history project, reunion events, and copies of Holsinger photographs. There is also a Preservation Piedmont Newsletter, a history of the Jefferson Preschool Center, an article, "We Shall Overcome," http://www.nps.gov/history/nr/travel/civilrights/intro.htm and an essay about the lack of historical sources on African American lives in Charlottesville. The entire essay can also be read online at http://www2.vcdh.virginia.edu/afam/aas405/syllabus/essay.html
  - 2001-2006 Jefferson School Newspaper clippings, 36 items (Box-folder 15:2)
  - [1950] n. d. Jefferson School Photographs, 3 items (Box-folder 15:3)
    Photocopies of students at Jefferson School
  - 2003 March-July Jefferson School Task Force Minutes, 26 items (Box-folder 15:4)
    There are Jefferson School Task Force minutes from April through July. Minutes from June 18 th are not included here but can be found with the Jefferson School Task Force Proposal A-N and minutes from January 3, 30, March 4, and March 13, 2003 meetings are located in the Jefferson School Task Force Proposal 0-Y. The minutes mention a set of guiding principles, and the Jefferson School as a historical site. (This issue is discussed throughout the Task Force minutes.) There are e-mails, notes, reports, transcript from a community held meeting, and a proposal from the Reunion Committee.
  - 2003 August Jefferson School Task Force Minutes, 14 items (Box-folder 15:5)
    They discussed the impact of other development downtown near the Jefferson School, sources of funding and anchor tenants that would offer multiple uses and fit within the historic culture of the site. They also discussed requesting an extension from City Council to finish their report. Also included is a Report & Recommendations of Social Service Non Profits in the area
  - 2003 September Jefferson School Task Force Minutes, 21 items (Box-folder 15:6)
    The minutes discuss the plans for a community held meeting. Included with the minutes are e-mails from facilitator, Jinni Benson of Mary Means & Associates, and long time community leader Grace Tinsley, maps, a power point with cost estimates, reports, and a site analysis of the Jefferson School building by Frazier Associates. There is a website for a school that was built in 1915 in Portland, Oregon which was renovated to be a hotel, gymnasium, restaurant, store and civic center, and it can be seen at http://www.mcmenamins.com/427-kennedy-school-home
  - 2003 October-December Jefferson School Task Force Minutes, 19 items (Box-folder 15:7)
    Included with the minutes are e-mails, a report by Lois Sandy, a report by Genevieve P. Keller, letters from potential tenants of the school, maps, revenue calculations, and a draft report to City Council from the Task Force. The minutes reveal discussions about expanding the streets around the Jefferson School, evaluation of the variety of options for use, search for a lead organization to run the facility, and the idea of connecting the Jefferson School with other historic sites in the area.
  - 2002 January-August Jefferson School Task Force Proposal 1-8, 1/5 notebook (Box-folder 16:1)
    The notebook is in reverse chronological order and is a proposal to City Council from Nancy O'Brien to act as facilitator of the Task Force. (included are photographs and a CD) City Council had placed a bid for proposals for a facilitator and chose Mary Means & Associates as the facilitator.
  - 2002-2003 Jefferson School Task Force Proposal A-N, 2/5 notebook (Box-folder 16:2)
    There is a list of Task Force Members, staff from City Council, a timeline, appraisal, tax credits, grants, research of best practices, community survey, correspondence, and minutes.
  - 2002-2003 Jefferson School Task Force Proposal O-Y, 3/5 notebook (Box-folder 16:3)
    There are minutes from February 10, 25, March 4, and March 13, 2003. The Task force worked towards finding our more about the history of the school, obtaining a historic register, relocation of programs at the school, maps and a list of individuals that were allowed to speak with the media.
  - 2002-2003 Jefferson School Task Force Goals, Proposal Z, 4/ 5 notebook (Box-folder 16:4)
    There are minutes from September 30, November 19, December 3, 31, 2002, January 6, 7, 14, 21, 28, 2003 Task Force meeting and a letter to City Council outlined the benefits of placing the school on the National Landmark register. There is also a list of project goals and ground rules for the Task Force. Topics include cost estimates for renovation, repairs, survey of existing conditions, tax credits, and housing options. There are several documents presenting facts about the National Register. Also included is a proposal from Mary Means & Associates to serve as facilitator for the Jefferson School Task Force.
  - 2002-2003 Jefferson School Task Force Proposal 1-15, 5/ 5 notebook (Box-folder 16:5)
    There is information about the original work of the task force including mission statements from the Citizens for Jefferson School.
  - 2003-2004 Jefferson School Task Force Report, 14 items (Box-folder 16:6)
    Included is a draft of the Jefferson School Task Force Report and recommendations of the task force
  - 2003-2005 Jefferson School Task Force Report, 5 items (Box-folder 17:1)
    Jefferson School Report on Historic Designation and Design Concept Update, and the final report to City Council with recommendations of the Jefferson School Task Force (Bringing Life Back to Historic Jefferson School) There are three photographs of the parking lot and city yard in front of the school.
  - 2002-2003 Jefferson School Task Force, 1 notebook (Box-folder 17:2)
    Included is information on other cultural centers, and schools, a Jefferson-Madison Regional Library fact sheet, e-mails, ideas for Jefferson Children and Family Center, and summaries from the education work group sessions.
  - 2002 January Jefferson School Exhibits A-H, 1 of 2 notebook (Box-folder 17:3)
    Included are capital plans for the City of Charlottesville
  - 2002 January Jefferson School Exhibits I-N, 2 of 2 notebook (Box-folder 17:4)
    Included in the notebook is an appraisal for the Jefferson School property, information for nomination of the school as a historic landmark, a community survey about uses for the school, copies of newspaper articles, estimate of project costs and survey of existing conditions, illustrations, guidelines for usage, history of the school, and information from the Citizens for Jefferson School (mission statement, and petition)
- Series V: Facilitator
  - 1975 Facilitator Monticello Area Community Action Agency, 10 items (Box-folder 17:5)
    There are a few monthly reports for MACAA. There is also a Request for a Proposal from MACAA for Organizational Consulting Services which was awarded to Nancy O'Brien. Included is the revised mission statement which O'Brien wrote for them
  - 1997 Facilitator Virginia Conservation Network, 2 items (Box-folder 17:6)
    Included is a report and a floppy disk
  - 2001 Facilitator for the Louisa County Resource Council, 1 item (Box-folder 17:7)
    There is a report [by Nancy O'Brien] titled, "The County of Louisa, Virginia Comprehensive Plan. The County Board of Supervisors wrapped the report in a red ribbon and gave it to Nancy O'Brien when she retired. They signed their names and wrote thank you notes on the inside front cover. Nancy attached a note saying that "getting this passed was a Herculean effort"
  - 2002-2003 Facilitator Louisa County Resource Council Retreat, 7 items (Box-folder 17:8)
    There is an agenda, planning strategies town meeting, and a synopsis
  - 2002 Facilitator Minority Health Project, 14 items (Box-folder 17:9)
    There is information about identifying minority health issues in the community
  - 2004 Facilitator Senior Center Focus Groups, 18 items (Box-folder 17:10)
    There are strategy meetings, notes and a report
- Series VI: Speeches
  - 1971; 1976-1977 Speeches and Press Releases, 27 items (Box-folder 18:1)
    There are speeches about running for office and her acceptance speech for City Council, a statement of Nancy O'Brien and K. Lane Kneedler, speeches to the Business Women's Club, Jefferson Society, First Christian Church, Ebenezer Baptist Church, Charlottesville High School Chapter of the National Honor Society, Charlottesville Public Schools, Virginia Nurses Association, Commencement at Piedmont Virginia Community College, Saint John Grand Lodge of Virginia, and speeches on Economic Development, South Fork Rivanna Reservoir, Services for the Ageing, Women in Political Process, Passing the ERA, and burying a time capsule at Vinegar Hill
  - 1978-1981 Speeches and Press Releases, 7 items (Box-folder 18:2)
    There are speeches to the Unitarian Church on "Civic Virtue, Monticello Toastmistress Club, University Baptist Church, and include subjects such as "Highrise for the Elderly," "Process Used to Construct the Downtown Shopping Mall," and "Piedmont Land Use"
  - 1986-2003 Speeches and Press Releases, 6 items (Box-folder 18:3)
    Speeches included are to the Virginia Society of Professional Nurses, a "Toast to Mitch Van Yahres," "Independence Day Exercises at Monticello," the Senior Center, and Historic Garden Week
  - 2005 Speeches, 4 items (Box-folder 18:4)
    There are speeches on Leadership, nomination of Karen Waters for one of the "Distinquished Dozen," celebration of the life of Mary Alice Gunter, and "Breaking Through Barriers" to the American Association of University Women
- Series VII: Scrapbooks
  - 1976 February-June Scrapbook pages, 1/4 (Box-folder 18:5)
    Newspaper clippings and correspondence
  - 1976 July-December Scrapbook pages, 2/4 (Box-folder 18:6)
    There are newspaper clippings and invitations. Also included is information on Queen England's visit. (Luncheon menu)
  - 1977 January-May Scrapbook pages, 3/4 notebook (Box-folder 18:7)
    Newspaper clippings
  - 1977 June-September Scrapbook pages, 4/4 notebook (Box-folder 19:1)
  - 1977 October-December Scrapbook pages, 1/4 notebook (Box-folder 19:2)
  - 1978 January-February Scrapbook pages, 2/4notebook (Box-folder 19:3)
  - 1978 March-June Scrapbook pages, 3/4 notebook (Box-folder 19:4)
  - 1978 July-December Scrapbook pages, 4/4 notebook (Box-folder 20:1)
  - 1979 January-May Scrapbook pages, 1/3 notebook (Box-folder 20:2)
  - 1979 June-December Scrapbook pages, 2/3 notebook (Box-folder 20:3)
    Newspaper clippings and a biography of Nancy O'Brien
  - 1980-1981 Scrapbook pages, 3/3 notebook (Box-folder 20:4)
  - n.d. Scrapbook photograph pages, 1 notebook (Box-folder 20:5)
  - 1978 Yearly Planner, 1 item (Box-folder 20:6)
  - 1993 Awards- McIntire Citizenship Award, 51 items (Box-folder 21:1)
    There are e-mails and numerous congratulation letters for receiving the Paul Goodloe McIntire Citizenship Award
  - 1993 Awards- McIntire Nominees, 46 items (Box-folder 21:2)
    There is information about Nancy O'Brien and other nominees for the McIntire Award
  - 2005-2006 Awards, 20 items (Box-folder 21:3)
    There are e-mails of congratulations for receiving the Drewary Brown Award, and the Bridge Builders Award
  - 1978-2001 Certificates, 11 items (Box-folder 21:4)
  - 1974-2003 Printed Materials, 16 items (Box-folder 21:5)
    There are newsletters from the Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission the University of Virginia Newsletter, Preservation Piedmont, Cville Magazine, Charlottesville Observer, League of Women's Voters, Chamber of Commerce, and a newsletter from the Westminster Presbyterian Church Oversize items include a UVA diploma, other certificates of appreciation and a brick with a plaque on it from the Charlottesville Historic Downtown Mall.
  - 1986 Trophies: Gift for Graduation from UVA, 1 item (Box-folder 22:1)
    A tile of the Rotunda that was a gift from John Connover and Virginia Daugherty (on Nancy O'Brien's graduation from the University of Virginia)
  - 2001 Trophies: Executive Director Award (Box-folder 22:2)
    Executive Director of the Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission Award
  - 2006 Trophies: Drewary J. Brown Award (Box-folder 22:3)
    Drewary J. Brown Award given by the Charlottesville Democratic Committee